Supun Nakandala

Phone: (+1) 812-558-6888 3232 EBU3B CSE Email: snakanda@eng.ucsd.edu 9500 Gilman Drive Web: https://scnakandala.github.io La Jolla, CA 92093

Research Interests My research interest lies broadly in the intersection of Systems and Machine Learning, an emerging area which is increasingly referred to as Machine Learning Systems. In this space I operate as a data management researcher. My Ph.D. thesis work focuses on developing query optimization-inspired abstractions, algorithms, and systems to improve efficiency, scalability, and usability of deep learning workloads.

Education

University of California, San Diego

Sept 2017 - (expected) March 2022

PhD, Computer Science.

Thesis Title: Multi-Query Optimization for Deep Learning Systems

Thesis Advisor: Arun Kumar

Committee Members: Arun Kumar (chair), Yannis Papakonstantinou, Geoffrey Voelker,

Lawrence Saul, Loki Natarajan

University of California, San Diego MSc, Computer Science. GPA: 3.97/4.00 Sept 2017 - June 2020

University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

Aug 2010 - April 2015

Bachelor of the Science of Engineering, Computer Science & Engineering.

GPA: 4.11/4.20.

Department Topper and Gold Medalist

Work Experience

Research Intern

June 2021 - Sept 2021

Data Management, Exploration, and Mining Group - Microsoft Research (Incoming Intern)

Software Engineering Intern

June 2020 - Sept 2020

Redshift - Amazon Web Services Mentor: Yannis Papakonstantinou

Designed and implemented components of Redshift ML, in-database ML feature of Redshift data warehouse, that went to public preview.

Research Intern

June 2019 - Sept 2019

Gray Systems Lab - Microsoft

Mentors: Matteo Interlandi, Markus Weimer

Designed and implemented Hummingbird system, a compiler for translating classical machine learning pipelines into tensor computations for unified and faster scoring of machine learning models.

Research Software Developer

Oct 2015 - Aug 2017

Science Gateways Research Center, Indiana University

Manager: Marlon Pierce

Contributed to the development of Apache Airavata system, which is a software framework to compose, manage, execute, and monitor computational applications and workflows on distributed computing resources such as local clusters, computational grids, and computing clouds.

Teaching Experience Teaching Assistant - Systems for Scalable Analytics UCSD - Winter 2020 UCSD - Spring 2019 Teaching Assistant - Advanced Data Analytics Systems

Conference Publications

Cerebro: A Layered Data Platform for Scalable Deep Learning

Arun Kumar, **Supun Nakandala**, Yuhao Zhang, Side Li, Advitya Gemawat, and Kabir Nagrecha

CIDR 2021 (Vision paper)

Cerebro: A Data System for Optimized Deep Learning Model Selection

Supun Nakandala, Yuhao Zhang, and Arun Kumar

VLDB 2020

A Tensor Compiler for Unified Machine Learning Prediction Serving

Supun Nakandala, Karla Saur, Gyeong-In Yu, Konstantinos Karanasos, Carlo Curino, Markus Weimer, and Matteo Interlandi

OSDI 2020

Vista: Declarative Feature Transfer from Deep CNNs at Scale

Supun Nakandala and Arun Kumar

SIGMOD 2020

Extending Relational Query Processing with ML Inference

Konstantinos Karanasos, Matteo Interlandi, Doris Xin, Fotis Psallidas, Rathijit Sen, Kwanghyun Park, Ivan Popivanov, **Supun Nakandala**, Subru Krishnan, Markus Weimer, Yuan Yu, Raghu Ramakrishnan, Carlo Curino CIDR 2020

Incremental and Approximate Inference for Faster Occlusion-based Deep CNN Explanations

Supun Nakandala, Arun Kumar, and Yannis Papakonstantinou SIGMOD 2019

Honorable Mention for Best Paper Award

Invited to TODS 2020

Invited to SIGMOD Research Highlight 2020

Gendered Conversation in a Social Game-Streaming Platform

Supun Nakandala, Giovani Cimpaglia, Norma Su, and Yong-Yeol Ahn AAAI ICWSM 2017

Apache Airavata Security Manager: Authentication and Authorization Implementations for a Multi-Tenant eScience Framework

 ${\bf Supun~Nakandala},$ Hasini Gunasinghe, Suresh Marru, and Marlon Pierce IEEE e-Science 2016

Journal Publications

The CNN Hip Accelerometer Posture (CHAP) Method for Classifying Sitting Patterns from Hip Accelerometers: A Validation Study in Older Adults

Mikael Anne*, **Supun Nakandala***, Marta M. Jankowska, Dori Rosenberg, Fatima Tuz-Zahra, John Bellettiere, Jordan Carlson, Paul R. Hibbing, Jingjing Zou, Andrea Z. LaCroix, Arun Kumar, and Loki Natarajan

Medicine & Science in Sports & Exercise, 2021

(* Co-First Author)

Supun Nakandala, Marta Jankowaska, Fatima Tuz-Zahra, John Bellettiere, Arun Kumar, and Loki Natarajan

Journal for the Measurement of Physical Behavior, 2021

Query Optimization for Faster Deep CNN Explanations Supun Nakandala, Arun Kumar, and Yannis Papakonstantinou SIGMOD Record 2020 (SIGMOD Research Highlight Award)

Incremental and Approximate Computations for Accelerating Deep CNN Inference Supun Nakandala, Kabir Nagrecha, Arun Kumar, and Yannis Papakonstantinou TODS 2020 (Invited Paper)

Workshop and Demo Publications

Compiling Classical ML Pipelines into Tensor Computations for One-size-fits-all Prediction Serving

Supun Nakandala, Gyeong-In Yu, Matteo Interlandi, and Markus Weimer NeurIPS 2019 MLSys Workshop

Cerebro: Efficient and Reproducible Model Selection on Deep Learning Systems Supun Nakandala, Yuhao Zhang, and Arun Kumar SIGMOD 2019 DEEM Workshop

 $Demonstration\ of\ Krypton:\ Optimized\ CNN\ Inference\ for\ Occlusion\mbox{-}based\ Deep\ CNN\ Explanations$

Allen Ordookhanians, Xin Li, **Supun Nakandala**, and Arun Kumar VLDB 2019 Demo | MLSys 2019 Demo

 $\begin{tabular}{ll} Materialization Trade-offs for Feature Transfer from Deep CNNs for Multimodal Data \\ Analytics \end{tabular}$

Supun Nakandala, Arun Kumar MLSys 2018 Short paper

Anatomy of the SEAGrid Science Gateway

Supun Nakandala, Sudhakar Pamidigantam, Suresh Marru, Marlon Pierce NSF XSEDE 2016

Pre-Prints

Nautilus: An Optimized System for Deep Learning-based Active Transfer Learning Supun Nakandala and Arun Kumar Under Preparation

Intermittent Human-in-the-loop Model Selection using Cerebro: A Demonstration Liangde Li, **Supun Nakandala**, and Arun Kumar Under Submission

Research Impact

Microsoft open-sourced Hummingbird system and uses it in ONNX ML Tools 2020 Ideas from project Cerebro integrated into MADlib/Greenplum by VMWare 2019 Cerebro system is being used by behavioral science researchers at UCSD 2019 "Gendered Conversation in a Social Game-Streaming Platform" paper gains lot of media attention and creates awareness about the bleak issue of sexism in online game streaming platforms 2017

APACHE AIRAVATA science gateways middleware and the SEAGRID science gateway are widely used by computational science researchers to execute and manage computational jobs on university clusters and national supercomputing infrastructure 2017

Patents

Pending US Patent Application: Query Optimization for Deep Convolutional Neural Network Inferences

Arun Kumar and Supun Nakandala

Pending US Patent Application: Accelerating Inference of Traditional ML Pipelines

with Neural Network Frameworks

Matteo Interlandi, Markus Weimer, Saeed Amizadeh, Konstantinos Karanasos, Supun Nakandala, Karla J. Saur, Carlo Aldo Curino and Gyeongin Yu

Service Program Committee:

VLDB: 2022

External Reviewer:

VLDB: 2019

Mentoring Student Research Projects:

Liangde Li, MS UCSD 2021

Allen Ordookhanians, MS UCSD 2019

Xin Li, MS UCSD 2019

Advitya Gemawat, BS UCSD 2021 Kabir Nagrecha, BS UCSD 2021

Scholarships and Awards

Student grant to attend OSDI 2020 $\,$

USENIX - 2020

NSF travel award to attend SIGMOD 2019

NSF - 2019

Gold Medal for the Best Academic Performance Uni Travel award to attend South Asia Workshop on Research

University of Moratuwa - 2015

Mahapola Higher Education Merit Scholarship

NUS Singapore - 2014 Govt. of Sri Lanka - 2010

Technical Talks

Cerebro: A Data System for Optimized Deep Learning Model Selection VLDB 2020; UCSD CNS Research Review 2020; SIGMOD 2019

A Tensor Compiler for Unified Machine Learning Prediction Serving

OSDI 2020; Microsoft Gray Systems Lab 2019; Google Brain ML+Compiler Reading Group 2021 (Invited)

Vista: Optimized System for Declarative Feature Transfer from Deep CNNs at Scale SIGMOD 2020; UCSD CNS Research Review 2018

Incremental and Approximate Inference for Faster Occlusion-based Deep CNN Explanations

SIGMOD 2019

Gendered Conversation in a Social Game Streaming Platform

AAAI ICWSM 2017; Indiana University Center for Complex Network and Systems Research 2017 (Invited)

Apache Airavata Sharing Service: A Tool for Enabling User Collaboration in Science Gateways

PEARC 2017

Apache Airavata Security Manager: Authentication and Authorization Implementations for a Multi-tenant e-Science Framework

IEEE e-Science 2016

Anatomy of SEAGrid Science Gateway

PEARC 2016